If you use Java, if you use cotlin,
chances are you still end up in
Intelligj. And since AI is all the hype
and it's so unpredictable like literally
two years ago, you give the same prompt
two times within 5 minutes gap, you get
a different answer. So somehow showing
the demos is very stressful with that.
When the likes of cursor and copilot and
a number of AI tools came out, it rocked
the world in terms of developers being
able to do all these amazing wonderful
things. Purser was the first one who
figured out this UX around the chat and
the code generation inside the editor.
Windsurf was the first to actually show
how it could be integrated in the ID
Corser and Windsurf and whoever else
they implemented that and I was talking
to my friends who use that and they say
this is all we need.
[Music]
Hello and welcome to another episode of
the AI native dev. I'm still here at
Devox and joining me is actually an old
friend from many years ago, Anton
Aropov. Anton, welcome to the native dev
first of all. Uh, happy to be here. We
go back many years. Um, we first met
each other. I don't think we met when I
was back in the IBM days, but I joined
this 2012.
2012. Yeah, that's Yeah, that's exactly
right. So, I joined Zero Turnaround in
in 2012. Zero turnaround for those who
don't know it's kind of like a it was a
productivity company that helped Java
developers uh a lot of was a very
interesting project we built
instrumenting agents for fast reloading
on of Java classes on the fly without
bringing down the JVM it was like a PHP
feel when you are using this tool so you
don't have to restart you make the
change you instantly see it in the in
the app and because back in the day as
well when app servers were pretty
sizable
Yeah, it took years and J bosses. I
remember we did some research and the
average startup time was 3 minutes. Wow.
3 minutes. It's the average. That's
right. The longest I have seen was over
30. I heard I heard 90 at one stage from
customer just just to reload their
server. So yeah, but luckily we're not
in those days anymore. And um so yeah,
people probably remember that tool as
JRebel for the Java devs there. Exactly.
You moved from there to Jet Brains. Yes,
I did. And um you were a massive power
user of Intelligj back in the day before
you worked for Jet Brains. I think it
was a really natural. It was a logical
move for me to go to Jet Brains. But my
first uh project wasn't Intelligj
because I thought I I want to learn new
stuff and then uh I actually uh joined
Team City team. Oh yes you did. That's
right. Yeah. For a couple of years I did
advocacy for team city providing
feedback to the product talking to the
users doing the webinars learning about
new technologies because I was always in
Java and CI is not only about Java it's
also about containerization
uh delivery different technologies even
PHP you know like Ruby Python whatever
else you you still need to run the tests
in CI you still need to run the build
whatever the jobs are a little bit
similar to me when I moved into sneak
Again, it was a more of an ecosystem
agnostic kind of move. Well, obviously
there were languages that were
supported, but you care less about any
specific ecosystem. And now, are you in
you moved into a cotlin for a little
while as well, right? Yes. Uh for 5
years I've been 5 years in cotlin. Uh so
I was like focused on cotlin 100% mostly
on the server side of it. Uh so if
you've been following the news about
cotlin, you probably have seen my face
speaking about new language features and
so on. I still do that. So at this
conference, I actually did a talk about
the new stuff coming in 2.2 and 2.4.
Well, Intelligj is always there. Yeah,
I'm just naturally always speaking about
IntelliJ because if you use Java, if you
use Scotland, chances are you still end
up in Intelligj and uh since AI is all
the hype and it's so unpredictable like
literally two years ago, you give the
same prompt two times uh within 5
minutes gap, you get a different answer.
So somehow showing the demos is very
stressful with that. Yeah. Yeah. So live
coding to another level, right? Yeah. So
my colleagues were all like, "Okay, we
need a demo. Let let Anon do that." I'm
like, "Okay, I I feel I'm feeling
adventurous." And somehow I got into
this more and more and now I I was told
to, "Okay, Anton, you probably just
enjoy this like and let's do it so that
you you cover all the AI in Intellain."
Yeah. Yeah. Right. So we have a multiple
multiple plugins actually there's four
four. So I know of two I know of. I know
of you probably don't realize but
there's four. I know of AI assistant. I
know of uh Juni. Yeah. What are the
other two? There are two embedded
plugins in intelligj. One is called uh
the full line completion FLCC. Okay. Y
that provides you the uh full line
completion. Now it's not only the full
line completion. It actually can provide
you multiple lines as well. But it's
those are short snippets. And the other
one where it all started is Gradzi which
is a spell checker. So the platform
behind AI assistant and uh partially
junior as well and all the completions
that we have is based on the project
that was called gradi for spellcheing.
Interesting. So let's talk about
actually let's take a step back and talk
about obviously with with Jet Brains
like Jet Brains is one of those kind of
companies that has a huge amount of
loyalty from its users around the
ide like from my background and your
background in Java in in the JVM
Intelligj is a hugely hugely used and
loved tool for developers. I hope it's
loved like we receive a lot of critical
feedback as well because like the more
users you have the more different use
cases you have the more uh unexpected
ways of using the product you will
actually discover and of course not all
the edge cases are covered sometimes
like everybody has bugs. Our bug tracker
is is full of different reports and like
we are receiving new ones new ones every
day. So yes like we have the feedback
from side to side like the very positive
and also some negative. Mhm. Uh but this
is about like any product out there I
think like popularity comes with a cost.
Yeah. Yeah. Absolutely. So you've got
four products today. I think it's fair
to say in the early in the very early
stages when when the likes of Cursor and
Copilot and and a number of AI tools
came out, it rocked the world in terms
of you know developers being able to do
all these amazing wonderful things. A
lot of the tools though kind of if you
look at obviously I think Rukode does it
as well, Cursor and a number of others
they fork VS code. Yeah. And effectively
if you want to use the if you want to
use the AI tool you go over to VS Code
and and you use that fork. Um how did
that kind of like not affect Jet Brains
but what was the reaction from from I
guess Jet Brains Intelligj users for
example to potentially think oh maybe I
could look at that because I want to use
cursor. It's a it's a bit of a tricky
one. Well today like among my friends I
see this pattern being used that they
use some VS for AI. Yeah. and they keep
IntelliJ open for inspecting the code,
navigating, doing the real development
with their hands as well. Of course,
well, it's a twofold situation. Like if
you take a step back and look at what
happened like two three years ago, the
first one was actually copilot, right,
with the completions. And uh I I was
hosting some live streams at that time
and I've got some guests who were using
copilot but for live coding especially
on the streams. It seemed that this
completion is getting in a way more than
it actually helping. It wasn't so smart
but the models weren't so smart. Now
they are getting smarter. You get better
quality from the product. Then those uh
forks appeared as well that incorporated
code generation into the tooling like
chatbased programming actually copilot x
appeared at that time as well. Now you
have a chat and you can ask a question
from uh from the LLM and it gives you
some answer and then you decide yourself
how would you what would you do with the
response right how can you integrate
with that into the project. Now, Pursor
was the first one who figured out this
UX around the chat and the code
generation inside the editor so that you
could iterate quicker. So, the first
stage is to get the answer to to
generate the code. The other the other
stage is to quickly put it in back into
the project and test it. Right. So,
cursor got it right and do that across
multi files as well. Exactly. Exactly.
But then but then you are the agent in
this case. you decide what to integrate
where how to iterate over the problem
that you have at hand and what tests to
run like do you have to run the whole
suit or whatever and now we have agents
wind surf was the first to actually show
uh how it could be integrated in the ID
you give it a high level task maybe
break it down into multiple tasks and
tell it to iterate over the problem it
figures generates the code integrates it
into the project runs the test So you
are now a supervisor. Mhm. Right. Great.
What was the reaction from uh from the
users? Of course they want the same
stuff in IntelliJ because they don't
want to move away in uh in unfamiliar
environment and and I think actually
from that Intelligj users or Jet Brains
users will probably I would say least
affected compared to other probably
across all the IDEs because I see that
loyalty for for people who who have
loved Intelligj over many many years and
and will actually resist change. They'll
fight they fight for that license. There
are also some things that in
intelligence some features implemented
that feel like AI but they are
predictable and implemented inside the
platform like for many many years. But
even this like very funny situation is
that we have been teaching people how to
refactor for many years or 20 years and
teaching them that renaming refactoring
is just this shift F6 shortcut. But now
people are like, "Oh, I want the next
edit prediction because it's a tab key."
And all you do, you do this tab driven
development. You just accept the changes
that the next edit prediction throws at
you. This is something we don't have in
the ID yet, but I know the team is
working on that. So soon we will have
that as well. But Corser and Windsurf
and whoever else they implemented that
and I was speaking like talking to my
friends who use that and they say this
is all we need. Yeah, we just need this
next edit prediction and it actually
replaces a lot of completions
functionality. So you know like
naturally you would type a dot and get a
completion list. With AI you get a full
line or a snippet that you can accept
line by line or so. It's still local.
Yeah. But completion does not have to be
local to the place where your cursor is.
It can be somewhere else in the file as
well. Like so if you are renaming uh
function name manually or next logical
step is that you rename the call sites
can be inside the file itself but they
can also be somewhere else in like in
the project. Uh all the call sites need
to be updated. This is something you
would normally do with refactoring but
then you have to learn all those
refactorings and people are lazy like
it's a natural thing like if you can do
it in this simplest way
possible hit the tap key this is like
the grunt work. Yeah. This is like you
you immediately become productive. So I
mistakes avoid mistakes. But this is a
very thin like very intimate UX problem.
I I spent some time a few hours straight
in Corser playing with this uh next edit
prediction and I felt like my head was
exploding with all those completions
streaming at me. Yeah. Like constantly
and I constantly had to like track what
is the next like prediction. Do I want
to accept it or not? Do I want to move
on or not? It's an interesting it's an
interesting model cuz do you get more
into the flow of just accepting
accepting accepting? actually turns into
more of a vibe coding because you're
just you're just agreeing with what it
does and then probably rely more on your
tests to say is actually doing the right
thing versus validating it line by line.
We're going to get lazy as developers,
right? But but like even there you you
still track the code, right? You are
still watching the code. uh compared to
VIP coding where you don't look at the
code with the agents where you just tell
it what you want to have and it
generates and you generally just check
sometimes like does it look right
because it can generate a lot of code
right it's like accepting a huge PR so I
think one of the effects that we will
have is that tools need to get better
for the PR acceptance like and the code
reviewing functionality
visualizing the code. So there were like
many attempts on visualizing and uh
getting an insight into the project like
how it's structured, what's the
architecture, what is the what are the
relationships between the components and
so on. And this is now becoming
critical. Yeah. So we probably will see
a lot of developments in that area as
well. Yeah. Yeah. Awesome. And debugging
as well.
debugging like when we have this TDD and
all this BDD practices, right? Why do
you need a debugger? You write the
tests. The test is your debugging tool,
right? And now, yes, the the LLMs can
generate the tests. And we have some uh
companies here offering exactly Yeah.
this functionality.
But now it probably comes to the
question, can you trust it? Yes. Is this
test really correct? Mhm. And what if
there is no test but you have the code?
It's almost going to get more critical
to review those tests. Yes. Than it is
the uh than it is the code that gets
generated. Right. Exactly. Let's jump
into the code. So we've talked a little
bit about kind of like the AI assistant
and Juny. Why don't we why don't we do a
quick demo um for those who are for
those who are listening only. We'll
describe what we're doing as we go.
Probably best viewed on on YouTube. Um
so so do check it out on YouTube as
well. But um let let's let's jump into
the code. Hi, I'm Bap, developer
advocate, AI Native Dev, and I'm taking
this quick moment to say that the
podcast unfortunately went on a strike
as Anton was about to demo. That said,
in our latest conference, AI native
DevCon, Anton was invited and share his
thought about agentic workflows and
demoed Juny, the latest AI coding agent
from Jet Brains. Let's cut straight to
that. Hello
everyone. I'm going to talk about AI
tooling in intelligj and uh my talk will
cover a few stages starting from the
completions in line completions cloud
completions various AI actions uh chat
modes in intelligj reaching out to the
agentic tool that we just recently
announced juni and uh I will walk you
through through the phases.
So let me actually start with uh the
sharing the screen. Uh we are here. So I
have intelligj but we will start from
the diagram. In fact I have a little
slide that's the only slide I have.
Everything else will be inside
intelligj. So those are the stages of AI
assistance inside the editors just my
creation. Okay. I haven't created all
the tools but it's something I came up
with uh for explaining the whole
subject. So on the left we have minimal
assistance from the tools where you have
like very minimal completions single
line completions or single statement
completions inside the editor and
reaching out to the most right end of
the spectrum. you have all this uh
agentic mode programming where you kind
of lose stop tracking what kind of code
you're actually creating by just uh
guiding the tool, what kind of
functionality you want to generate and
we we start with a very basic one. So we
start with the minimal assistance from
the tooling. Let's see how it looks like
inside. So I have a spring boot
application and it's a very minimal one.
It's just one
controller. There are a few
implementations of the algorithm
interface. They are just geometry
geometry filters basically. And let's
say I want to implement functionality
that will select the implementation
based on a configuration option. So
that's the scenario we're trying to
implement. And at the moment I assume
that I I'm really well aware of what
kind of code I want to write and I don't
need AI tool to actually write the code
for me. I want to do it myself. I want
to stay in the control. So what kind of
code would I write here? So maybe a
function function that
selects
select
algorithm by a property that is injected
from the configuration and that's going
to be something like this. Uh there's
the dollar. I got to type a property
name. algorithm type and then property
parameter name should be type uh of type
string string and well I as you see I'm
not really getting a lot of assistance
by the AI yet
uh that's going to be a
bin right there and that's going to be
uh an algorithm. So we first time we see
some completion happening right here at
the end of the line because uh what is
happening right now as I type there is a
local model working inside the
IDE provided by a plug-in called full
line completion that looks at the code
skipping the comments that it sees above
the cursor in the same file and tries to
come up with suggestion. In fact, I can
visualize what is happening. Let me
complete this line with an internal tool
uh that I have installed for myself. So
there are stats happening. This is
something I installed just to visualize
for for this demo to visualize what is
happening when I hit the uh buttons and
uh the ID is working on providing the uh
different suggestions. So uh as I type
here I I know exactly what code I want
to type right. I want to check for the
value of the string and if it matches
some sort of a value I would return a
class or a type instance. So
return and as you can see uh on the
bottom right uh the model has calculated
that with probability of 36% the next
statement that should satisfy my
requirement is going to be when with the
type subject and it also renders it in
the editor. That's cool cool information
for me to check how the AI completion
works. But let's see how how it works
like uh for the next statements I'm
going to type. As you can see uh it's it
suggest it found some suggestion by the
model that is working on my machine
right now. Uh but this suggestion
doesn't seem to be relevant. It might be
red code. It might be the like
irrelevant code maybe even whatever the
model generates. So for this kind of
workflow where I'm exactly aware what
kind of code I want to write, I just
need very fast completions to to help me
w with the task that I'm currently
working on and not to get in the way.
That's the most annoying thing when the
tool is getting in the way. We would
rather not show you any completion than
show you something incorrect or
something that is hallucinated. So if I
continue uh let's say quick how is one
of the values I want to get I can see
that the model is generating
something and quick hole is the model
uh I want to get an instance on the next
line it already suggests something that
is relevant and the code is not read so
I can accept it and very minimal that's
the very start of the AI assisted
programming inside uh intellig idea and
it's configurable. We have options uh
for inline completions where you can
enable or disable full line completions
based on the language and download the
relevant models. I currently have all of
them downloaded. Therefore, uh they just
display as checkboxes. But normally you
would have like a download button there.
We also have another step in in the
story where we can uh say that we know
what we want to get but we are too lazy
to type and uh we we want to get uh
larger code snippets from the models as
an assistance. So we can enable the
cloud completion suggestions. They can
suggest full snippets of code there.
There there are limits of course it will
not generate like 1,000 lines of code
but it will generate sensible code
snippets that you can accept partially
uh token by token or line by line and it
has a few uh levels of configurations
where you want the filter that works
inside the ID to filter out more to
allow less red code or let's say less
creative code that then you would select
the focused mode for this completion or
you want to get more creative and uh you
are fine of getting some interesting
code snippets from the mode. I have
currently enabled the balance mode.
Let's see how it works. I feel
adventurous today. So I have enabled
cloud completion and let's see how it
behaves with the same uh scenario that I
just had. So previously as I said the
full line completion would ignore the
comments. So it would only look at the
code snippets. But here I am or I
already added a comment of a function
that I want to write. Uh and the cloud
completion would account for that. So if
I just type it here, it already sees
that well there are implementations of
the algorithm. There is a interface we
are in the context of spring boot
application. we want to read a
configuration option and so on. And it
comes up with this full complete correct
code snippet where I could now accept
either
partially either
partially let's see uh I have something
with my uh keyboard right now or just
completely uh accepting those snippets
as is. Maybe I don't want some snippets,
some part of the snippet and uh I would
rather throw an exception if uh if I
don't match any of the values in from
the configuration and uh yeah currently
you can see that Melum is the completion
provider in the diagnostics right here
in in the bottom left a completion model
that we are we we recently open sourced
uh to the community. You can download it
and experiment with that as well. So as
you can see we have two levels already
of completions where where I know
exactly what I want to do and I want to
control every statement or I can lose
the ants up a little bit and uh uh I'm
fine with the completion generating
various code snippets like in multiple
lines of code. Let's go further. So the
next level is in editor generation with
minimalistic prompts meaning that you
are still uh focused on the code that
you're currently writing. Assume um
let's try generate generating a function
that would split a list of values for
us.
Split a function function or a utility
function to split a list of elements
into a list of lists of
elements by
an example element. So this would invoke
a local code generation and it's kind of
similar to the snippet completion that
we just saw. The difference is that the
completion would run or generate the
code in the place of the cursor but
inline code generation would actually
span uh across the file. It might add
imports. It might change the function
names. It might split functions. it
might generate some additional
components for for this to
work and of course it's also double
checked with for for the red code for
the relevance and so on. So now now we
have the patch right in the in the code
we can do some follow-ups here to
correct
our requirements to the generated code.
Maybe what I see here is not uh exactly
corresponding to what I want. uh maybe I
want to add extra constraints or I can
just accept it. Uh, of course further on
I can either regenerate this code
somehow say that I don't want functional
style or vice versa I want it to be
mutable uh or call start calling the AI
actions and the AI actions actually
start getting you out of the current
screen uh current file and uh maybe
generate some code outside of that file.
So for instance we we can ask it to
generate unit tests. So currently what
is happening the the AI assistant
matched the name or the the suffix of
the file uh that we that we used to call
the action from and it created a
relevant name for the test file and
created a few test cases for me to uh to
satisfy the functionality that I just
generated for for that function. As you
can see, we already loosening our
control a little bit more. We are not
focusing on a single line of code. We
are not focusing even on a local snippet
of code. We are now uh generating the
code in different places of the file and
even in different
files. Let's uh accept that. I'm not
sure if the tests would fail or not.
Let's assume that some of them should
fail, some of them probably will
pass. Uh but uh currently our goal is
not to test the code. The goal is to
explain at which stage are we. So we
generated the code inside the editor. In
fact, we can move on and uh look at the
chat now. So from this point on we are
getting out of the local file. We are
shifting our focus out of the editor. As
you can see the tests uh some of the
tests failed. Some of the tests uh
didn't fail but uh uh we we we we can
take the different flow and start fixing
them and asking the AI assistant how to
fix them. That's that's not in focus
right now. So let's get ourselves into
the chat. How can we do that? For
instance, the uh function that we just
generated this one. We can ask the uh AI
assistant to start doing something with
this snippet of code like start chat
using the selection.
We can either take the full file there
or adjust a function and ask the
assistant to do something with with this
code like transform it or maybe test it
somehow differently suggest something.
There is now a dilemma not really a
dilemma but there is a one important you
have to account for is that by default
the chat would not look into the whole
project right it we just asked it to do
something with a little snippet of code
so we already take this action to
isolate it uh but we can choose to tell
it to look at the whole code days please
uh whenever action I uh ask you to two,
please scan the project for the relevant
for the relevance of my query and maybe
populate the context with additional
information from the source code
depending what what will I ask for. So
maybe I will ask to rewrite rewrite this
code uh in
imperative style.
the uh what will happen the chat will
retransform my query ask the platform if
there are any relevant resources that we
can add into the context. Currently
there were no additional uh files
attached only the selection and the
current file actually and then we just
got the response. So at this point we
are um kind of an agent right now. We
are the agent. we take the decision what
kind of code do we want to integrate
back into the
project what uh tests we have to run to
assure that the code is correct and so
on. So there is a an extra mode for
figuring out uh or automating
integration of the code generated uh
model generated code back into the
project. We are currently in the chat
mode but we could have automated that as
well. So there is a beta feature. I'm
not going to run that uh at the moment
because we want to get to aentic
workflows quicker. But at this point I
can just tell uh the AI assistant to
integrate the code correctly and uh it
will display me the diff that uh applies
applies the code snippet. And uh just to
quickly demonstrate what could happen.
Uh so we we're going to switch into
codebase mode. uh we're going to tell
the chat that it can observe whatever uh
we have in the project. Yes. Sorry,
Anton. Um this is super exciting and and
and and just wanted to flag very very
quickly that there's a lot of people who
are asking you a ton of very relevant
question and we are jumping in one
minute with the next talk. I have tried
to curate like some of these questions.
So I'm just going to in the next one
minute if you can try to answer multiple
questions at once. So at least these
were the most relevant. Um
first of all we've had a couple of
people wanting to ask you uh and I think
you mentioned it throughout your talk of
like what libraries were used but uh
could you restate uh what Jet Brains
like AI assistant and like Juny like
what stack is it based on? What
languages is it based on? And a very
quick followup like how does Juny
understand like the legacy system and
like the constraints uh for each uh
enterprise or like a company or project.
Right. So we have two uh plugins. I have
been showing only the part for the AI
assistant and I just executed the query
for Juny to run on the screen while I'm
answering the question. AI assistant
provides completion the model selector.
you can chat with your project and uh
you are the agent who decides what kind
of code to integrate and what tests to
run. Juni in contrast just automates all
that for you. So it will iterate on the
on the problem that you have asked for.
Like for instance in in this workflow
that I just uh started I asked Juny to
implement the persistence layer which
means that it will span the the code
changes will span across the entire
project starting from the controller to
services configuration files build files
maybe for adding the additional uh
libraries and so on. So the stack uh you
mean the implementation probably then uh
it's all implemented in cotlin of course
because most of the uh plugins that we
build and like we we develop for
intelligj platform they are built with
cotlin
uh it works for any languages but for
junior specifically what we want to do
is to be able to integrate with the
platform specific or technology specific
specific tools. Meaning if I generate
code for Java, I should be able to uh
run a Java compiler or Java llinter or
some Java build tool like Maven or
Gradle and get uh maybe run the tests.
So I need to integrate with uh testr
runner and so on and that is technology
specific right. So uh for Juny we do
that for Juny it depends what kind of
technology you use in the project.
However code generation doesn't depend
on that. So even if Juny does not
support some technology like running
Python tests for inside intelligj maybe
because it's implemented for PyCharm uh
Juni is still able to generate the code
that you ask for uh even though it's not
supported inside the platform. For
instance, you you may want to generate
some C++ code in uh in inside IntelligJ
and there is no C++ tooling by default.
So that's possible. Wonderful. Thank you
so much for for explaining all that
Anton. And yeah, like I think a lot of
us started coding with Jet Brains and
we're just all super excited that Juni
is out. Uh so yeah, excited to see where
all that is going to go. But yeah,
fantastic talk. Super cool session. I
think everybody really really enjoyed
it. So thank you so much Anton. Thank
you.
[Music]